[Music]
hello everybody greetings to everyone
good day good evening wherever you are
and welcome to the 74th live episode of
ask abidjit
i can see all your comments very nice to
see you all let me see what is there
yuvraj garg mayank
aniket harsh jain krishna killer joker
foreign and many many many people good
evening good day to all of you it's
great to have you with
us tonight
so as you know today is a live chat
episode i'm gonna be taking your
questions and comments
from the live chat which is in front of
me
so be ready with your questions and go
ahead ask your questions and
and i will also take a few questions
from the comments that you all have put
in the past just to keep a nice mix
going but most of the questions will be
from the
uh live chat
so let us see
we sometimes see a guitar in the
background of your videos do you play
the guitar yes i play the guitar but
off late i have not played much i am
kind of out of touch with it because no
time but yes i'm a big fan of music and
you could say i'm an amateur musician to
some extent
right
um what questions do we have
who are the hazara people what is their
origin do they have connections to
indians and ethnicity please demonstrate
through maps i can't pull out the
relevant maps right now on demand that's
not possible
but i can answer your question
so the hazara people
are most likely the descendants of the
soldiers of the mongols the soldiers of
chinggis khan so exactly 800 years ago
slightly more than 800 years ago
there was this great battle in uh
in punjab
between ching is khan and the fugitive
kharismi
so what had happened is that
in 1221 a.d
chungishkhan invaded the khwarasm empire
in retaliation for their
terrible actions
he
conquered the quran quran empire he
destroyed it essentially totally
uh the shah of quran ran away in one
direction he eventually died in the
caspian sea
and his son
and his son jalal didn't whereas me he
fled
southwards and eastwards towards india
so ching is khan he sent his army to
pursue him
and eventually chingaskhan himself
caught up with jalaladdin and he
defeated him
on the banks of the indus river
his entire army was destroyed and
jalaluddin fled fled into india and
chinese khan did not bother with
pursuing him because the army was
destroyed so then
he had invaded
he had come into punjab via afghanistan
northern india gandhar so while going
back to china because there was a
chinese rebellion underway already so to
go by while going back to china he left
behind some soldiers
in afghanistan in gandhar to administer
the region because he had conquered it
so most likely the hazara people
are the descendants
of these
uh administrators and soldiers of
chinggis khan who are left behind to
administer
the region
so
in the mongol army the smallest i mean
there were many divisions of the army
but
one of the divisions was one thousand
soldiers
i think the ten thousand soldier
division was called two men
and there was also a one thousand
soldier division of the mongol army so i
think the hazaras are named after this
thousand soldier garrison formation or
that something like that that's what is
believed
now there are some people who will claim
that don call i mean many hazaras claim
that we are not mongols we are afghans
and all
they are afghans of course today they
are the citizens of afghanistan but the
ancestry is clearly a mongol in origin i
am not sure if genetic tests have been
done but most likely even if those have
been done we will find they find that
they are descendants of mongols they
also look different they look more like
mongols than north indians or afghans
right than pashtuns
so that is the uh
origin of the
hazara people do they have connections
to indians via ethnicity not really
today ethnicities are mixed in
afghanistan because of the history of
the past one thousand years
so i am sure some azaras have some
pashtun blood also and some uzbek tajik
blood etc but overall they are a
distinct ethnicity they are not closely
related ethnically to the pashtuns who
are an offshoot of the
overall indian population
so
that is the answer to your question sir
all right let's take some other
questions
manish kumar says how gandhi freed india
if not gandhi then why british give us
freedom i'm not sure what it means but i
have spoken at length about this so you
can look at my older videos
where did r1a1 originate from it
originated from india the indian
subcontinent it's a descendant of the uh
of the haplogroup event it's it's an
eventual descendant of the haplogroup f
which is an indian or origin
haplogroup
right what else what else what else what
else
um
do i have to answer this which
civilization was first egyptian and
indian
i think we all know the answer the
oldest known civilization on the planet
and the oldest continuously existing
civilization on the planet both are the
indian civilization
india civilization we have
archaeological evidence of cultural
continuity for around 10 000 years and
we haven't done proper archaeological
research in india the more we do the
more we'll find so actually india
civilization may go back 15 20 000 years
genetically we have the same lineages
which are alive today in us those are at
least 20 25 000 years old and the
ancestral lineage is around 70 000 years
old so the oldest civilization
archaeologically culturally
civilizationally and genetically is
india
in one of the interviews mr gohan
historian who says his historian
historian said that india doesn't belong
to any particular religion or a language
how true is this comment mr gohan is not
to be taken seriously that's all i can
say
okay was there any indian traveler who
went out of india in ancient times was
there any indian like ibm
marco polo etc i didn't hear any name if
not why we know indians had contacts
with the roman empire 2000 years ago
indians were
were sailing to rome
and uh say selling
trading
they were selling spices and other other
commodities which were manufactured in
india and they were taking back gold to
india we have extensive evidence of that
right uh we there is a there is uh there
is this statue which was found i think
in pompeii
it is a lakshmi statue most believe it's
clearly an indian origin statue either
it is from gandhara or it is from the
chandra ketuga region of bengal so again
there is evidence of indians there
we know that that indians had contacts
with
trade and other contacts with uh with
egypt india is a much older civilization
than egypt we know that around four
thousand years before today four four
and a half thousand years before today
an indian genetic component entered
australia
we know it it is it is proven beyond any
doubt all aboriginal or indigenous
australians have about 10
indian dna
right we know the extensive
uh
contacts between india and southeast
asia starting about three thousand years
ago at least via kalinga
trade contacts
it is still commemorated in the
bandana and the bali yatra and all that
so there are there have been thousands
and thousands maybe tens of thousands of
indians who went all across the known
world in ancient times thousands of
years before today we know that the
indian cattle
uh
were introduced into africa in two waves
one is about four thousand years ago in
egypt and one is about ten thousand
years before today
and these cattle don't migrate on their
own okay let's go for a migration or
voyage no these are domestic cattle
these are the zebu cattle the indian
cattle
the big humped bull you've seen right on
the indus valley seals
saraswati valley says that's that's one
so that
introduction into africa it first
happened about 10 000 years ago so
clearly indians took those cattle
into africa so these are some of the uh
things i can tell you there's much more
if you go into further detail lots and
lots of waves migrations and also so on
so indians traveled all over the known
world in ancient times
why are the names no longer recorded
because we lost all our records a
thousand years ago when all the temp
when all the temples the libraries the
universes were all destroyed by the
turks
we allowed this to happen that's why we
don't have any names that's why you
don't hear any name
but there is clear evidence of indians
being present all across the ancient
world
thousands of years before today
right max gaming says please tell us
about sanam hazem in manipur the
indigenous methi religion
religion and its connections and
influence from hinduism so tsunamism is
it's not an ism
it's a polytheistic belief system
uh the great
it's at least minimum two thousand years
old mini minimum maybe three and a half
thousand old years old or maybe even
before that
so the
the major deities are pakhamba and
sanamahi
dragon king or or the
or the snake snake king
is
he's supposed to be the ancestor of all
the metha people manipuri people right
so
and there is an entire
pantheon of gods
or divinities around him
it's it's it's a polytheistic belief
system there's also elements of nature
worship
ancestor worship and all that
so it is
a full-fledged polytheistic belief
system it is the indigenous belief
system of the methi people of manipur
now
manipur as you know is part of
what we call northeast india
and we know that
indian culture spread far and wide
across southeast asia for for at least
around 3000 years right
so it is no surprise that there are
elements of hinduism in manipur there
have been influences because like it's
right here
so influences have been there
neighboring burma is also like fully
influenced by indian culture now it's
called buddhism but if you look in to
detail there are elements of hinduism
throughout burma
thailand also is called a buddhist
country but there's so much
hinduism in there as well which is now
termed as buddhism
so uh
the story is that
there is this king
what was his name bhaga chandra
so bhaga chandra officially decreed
under the uh influence of a
gaudiya vaishnava preacher called
not preacher a priest whose name was
shantidas
gosai
so uh this king ching tang khumba or
bhaga chandra he came under the
influence of this bengali priest
and he officially declared
gaudiya vaishnavism to be the official
state uh
religion
so to say of manipur
so that happened i don't know about 400
350 or 400 years ago
obviously
there were vaisnava temples etc in
manipur before that also his ancestors
also had some connection with hinduism
and the influence has has always been
there for
thousands of years in this region
so officially it became the state
religion
about
somewhere around that time
and um
and then what happened is that sanamism
wasn't stamped out there is a story of
the sacred books of the
uh tsunamism they called the puyas that
were burned by this guy shantidas gosai
that's nonsense the king if it happened
it was a king who decreed that it to be
done so you can't blame chant shrante
that's gosai for that
but what happened is that my
vaishnavism gowdy evasionism became the
official state religion and it
essentially got syncretized with
sanamism so if you look at the
meta people today they in one corner of
the house they will have the gods which
will be lord krishna maybe
radha
and also the sadamahi gods as well so
that's the way it is you know
so these are not exclusive belief
systems there is no exclusivism in
polytheism look at russia i'm sorry not
russia
look at japan shinto
and buddhism and hindu hinduism are all
beautifully synchronized synchronized
together right so that's the same sort
of thing you see you find all across
asia wherever indian culture has gone it
has syncretized and intermingled with
the local
culture so in manipur today mo the metis
are considered to be hindus some
nowadays say that we are not hindus we
are
uh we believe only in tsunamis and so on
because of the marxist influence and all
that
so
the essential thing is that hinduism is
not an intrusive religion
or or
something that was imposed upon the
people the king himself accepted it and
people also practiced it right so that's
the story in in brief uh it's a very
fascinating
part of india and very interesting
history i would recommend you guys all
study more about it um if you can find
the
find
sources and references online
so nice good question
all right let um
what kind of feminism is needed in india
is what samprathi goswami asks we don't
need feminism in india feminism has a
completely different context it emerged
out of a different environment in it
feminism originates
in the english-speaking world mainly in
north america but also to some extent in
the uk in england and we know what sort
of lives women led over there they were
terribly terribly terribly oppressed
so it emerged about 200 or so years ago
slowly by
different people i can go into that in
detail i don't remember the names right
now of the ladies who started that but
uh
so it emerged it was necessitated by the
oppressive environment in which women
lived
there wasn't they had no rights they had
no voting rights they had no property
rights they were essentially just slaves
or servants or property of the men they
married
or they or their fathers
and so on so this movement arose out of
that
and
it was needed it was a legitimate and
much needed movement and it did
emancipate women greatly over time in
the west in the west where it was needed
in india women have never been oppressed
yes in the past 1 000 years certain
things have crept into indian society
out of a need to survive
women had to start putting this parda
and staying indoors because of certain
reasons
that turks invaded and occupied india
they had a very different way of looking
at women
they did not look at women as
individuals as human beings they looked
at them as pieces of meat as property
and an uncovered woman is fair game for
any kind of behavior
so that's why indian women had to go
indoors and hide indoors and if they
went out there to cover their faces and
bodies and all that nonsense
right
so that doesn't necessitate feminism
what we need in india is a re is a
return to indian values
indian values
put women it they gave women the highest
of respect
the highest of respect right
so
no feminism is needed in india india
doesn't require feminism it doesn't
belong in the it doesn't belong in the
indian context at all everything is
context specific
it emerged in the west because of the
context because of the the environment
that women were in the situation that
women were in
women are not oppressed in india of
course there are certain sections of
society where they
they have other
they face other problems but overall if
you look at indian culture it
perceives women with the highest of
respect in the highest of regard
and there is no question of needing some
emancipation or empowerment yes certain
problems have crept into indian society
those need to be addressed but not with
western medicine we just need to go back
to our own culture and values that's all
so that's what i have to say but it's a
interesting question some pretty good
question
okay raj vardhan says what's the science
what was the science behind the
extraordinary structures of our ancient
temples why every village has its own
deity is there a science behind it there
is no science in religion okay there is
no science in faith in culture culture
and spirituality and philosophy are
separate from science
science has always been an integral part
of indian civilization because for a
civilization to make material progress
you need science
but when it comes to deities and all
there's no science behind that there is
culture behind that culture civilization
and spirituality that is what
governs the um
belief system and all that right now
what about the extraordinary structures
of our ancient temples it's all geometry
it's all architecture and it's all about
understanding how to use
rock
most of our ancient temples were made
out of rock many monolithic temples
exist carved out of a single rock look
at the great kailash temple in elora
it's carved out of a single rock face
and so on so our ancestors were
extraordinarily gifted they were they
were great at architecture and
understanding the composition of rock
and how to use
geometry to to create various kinds of
shapes
and of course there was a certain
way a certain manner in which temples
were aligned it was all
uh
based on the human form actually
so there's a whole different uh aspect
to that maybe i can call some architect
who understands this and we can have a
discussion about that because this is a
very interesting topic actually
so let me put that on my to-do list
for you to get more details and a proper
perspective about this it's a
fascinating topic
so but for now in in brief this is what
i can tell you
okay what else okay let me take a couple
of questions from the previous comments
so let me remove this yes okay and let's
take a question from a comment
how can i find my passion
how do you find your passion i'm
expecting shreya that you're quite young
must be
let's say you're a teenager or let's say
you're 20 or so so at a young age it's
not
often that you know exactly what you
want to do in your life
when you're young you're kind of
clueless you're looking around every
week you find some new passion but then
you know it kind of dissipates and then
you want something else so how do you
find your true
passion your true purpose in life
how do you know which food you like the
best
if you just eat dal chawal every day
will you know which food is the best for
in your opinion
if you just eat one or two kinds of food
every single day day in day out week in
week out month and month out then you
will never know what's out there in the
world and you will never develop your
palate
and you will never realize you will not
figure out what food you like the best
so to figure out what food you like the
best you have to try all kinds of
different dishes
you have to explore
you have to go to taste test
different and try different cuisines
different uh varieties of food and then
over time you'll figure out what you
like the best similarly
to find your passion in life to find a
purpose in life you try lots of
different things
don't stick to a narrow road
try lots of different things explore
lots of different things when you're
young you can afford to try lots of
different things
right
try
uh different careers in different
industries give everything like
i i know it's it's not as easy as it
sounds
because you cannot just keep on changing
careers all the time
but let's say you're a student and you
want to understand what thing is suited
best for you try
to learn on the side different things
try
graphic design computer coding
programming
uh
being a chef cooking
or whatever comes to your mind right
whatever you think would be interesting
for you
follow your curiosity for follow your
interest and try lots of different
things only then will you be able to
figure out eventually after like three
four five years maybe or maybe sooner if
you're lucky what your true passion is
so that's what you have to do you have
to give different things a chance and
try lots of different things that's how
you figure out what your passion is now
back to the comments back to the live
live chat
history maths
i don't know what that is
is marxism good for india marxism is
good for nobody
why is it that most renowned spiritual
figures
most of them are from bengal reason uh
vivekananda shirley the chaitanya
paramount yoga and the ramakrishna there
are so many from outside bengal but you
know what
bengal is the first place the british
colonized essentially
right
so you got lots of people emerging out
of bengal the first really properly
colonized place lots of people who wrote
in english
and today everything is in english so we
kind of see everything coming from
bengal so we think the bengalis are i'm
not saying bengalis are not great or
anything all indians are great okay
but i refuse to believe that only one
portion of india is somehow
intellectually superior all
intellectuals come from this place what
they think today and i will think
tomorrow that is nonsense
all indians are great all indians are
superior bengals are not special
but this is the image that has been
created
by the uh
by the agents of colonization i would
say
there are lots and lots of great people
from all across india who have been
totally neglected marginalized etc
have you heard of adi shankaracharya was
it from bengal
i would say that he eclipses all these
people that you have mentioned in this
comment no disrespect to any of them but
adi shankaracharya was a million times
greater than any of them
and i can think of so many other people
so you know what it's not like that
it's the it's a perception that has been
created in our minds by the
establishment by the historians
by the eminent histories etc that bengal
is somehow special bengal is as great as
the rest of india
all of india is great you have great
people all across india there are many
even today who are not known i'm sure we
need to discover them
so that is what i can say my friends
how did marxism start yeah good question
it started with marx and engels but
there's a whole lineage before that this
hegels whose
ideas max adopted and brought them
forward and after max ingles continued i
mean
max was a guy who never worked in his
entire life
even though he spoke about the
uh workers and all that but he never
worked a single day in his life he was
supported by his best friend friedrich
engels friedrich was it i think so yeah
so and engels supported marx with the
prophets of capitalism
so marx wrote this communist manifesto
he wrote das kapital in the middle of
the 19th century and then
it was it did not really receive much of
a reception nobody cared but somehow
in russia this kind of took off and
eventually
it was
appropriated in a certain way
to create a dictatorship but not quite
the dictatorship of the proletariat and
so on you know so it's a it's a
interesting chapter of history and
marxism is still relevant today because
so many people are still marxists they
believe that you know we need a
classless society where everybody is
equal that's nonsense my friends there
is no such thing as equality in the
world no two people are equal you can
give them equal rights
yeah
but no two people are equal we celebrate
inequality why do we play cricket
do we want to celebrate equality
everybody gets the same
score and everything no we want to
celebrate who's better why do we have
world cup football to celebrate
inequality
everybody gets the same chance but then
the best will
win
right
why do you have exams in school
are you celebrating equality does
everybody get the same marks does
everybody get the same first rank nope
some fail some pass some some rise to
the top it's a celebration of inequality
the world is an inequal place
you can't have a classless society
any functioning society is going to
be a hierarchy any
well-functioning organization is going
to be hierarchical in nature it's just
the way it is whether you like it or not
is immaterial facts don't care about
anyone's feelings these are facts so
marxism
it's very easy to mislead people with
marxism you know it sounds it sounds so
nice everybody should be equal there
should be no class no no upper class
lower class nothing in society
but even in marxist societies you will
find hierarchies
all right so
so that's just what i can say in brief
about this but yeah that's just how it
is
um
why indian culture influenced southeast
asia so much and even japan but not
chinese culture
who says india did not influence chinese
culture
who says that
china today has the world's largest
population of buddhists more than 200
million
china is incredibly deeply influenced by
indian culture for 2000 years
you need to study history a little bit
more maybe you can
see some of my previous videos i've
spoken about this
and this is extensively well known how
deeply india influenced china yes the
chinese emperors did not follow buddhism
they followed confucianism and then
they practiced a mix
a certain kind of mix of legalism
and
confucianism
both are atheistic doctrines but the
khan people
most of them followed buddhism that the
communists stamped that out
even kung fu what you call kung fu
originated in india look up the story so
you know
uh interesting that you feel this way
but that is certainly not consistent
with the facts
right let's see something else
um
there's a statue in germany which has a
lion's head
and a human body like narasimha bhagwan
and the statue is about 40 000 years old
it doesn't mean that hinduism is 40 000
years old
what's the evidence that this is a hindu
statue
it's a it's a the statue is a depiction
of a lion
it's a lion's face clearly standing on
two legs like a human being
but
is there anything else that associates
this with hinduism or is it just a
coincidence
because you did you did have lions in
europe thousands of years ago
so you know what this is just one data
point to
make to have a pattern you need multiple
data points with one data point you
cannot establish a pattern
and to
say that there was hinduism there you
need a pattern you need at least three
four minimum data points which all point
in the same direction of hinduism
because hinduism is not just narasimha
there are so many other uh elements to
hinduism
to the practice of hinduism
so i would not agree that this this is a
an indication of hinduism being
practiced 40 000 years ago
it is just a statue of a lion with with
a human-like body
so
that's that's my perspective about this
i'm sure many people disagree which you
are free to do
but this is how i feel about this
all right
after the incident of julian wallabag
massacre what happened to those indian
soldiers who killed our own people where
they punished afterwards in 1947 nothing
happened to them nothing whatsoever they
were following the orders of the indian
government
of the british indian government and the
post-47 government is nothing but a
continuation of the colonial british raj
so absolutely nothing happened to those
people i believe it was a good
harassment
i think so if i'm mistaken i apologize
but i think
it was the gurkha regiment or or
if it was not the good encouragement
those were gurkha soldiers
right
is what is that
what is that vacant space where the
universe is expanding what will happen
if two universes collapse
will they destroy each other or will we
will be submerged all speculation we
don't know
no physicist can give you a definitive
answer to these questions no none
whatsoever
we don't know if there is anything
outside the universe we don't know
we don't even know how large of our
universe is we have we there are some
speculative
calculations or something like that but
about 45 trillion
light years across that speculation
based upon some hypothetical
calculations but we don't know how large
our universe is we don't know what lies
beyond our universe we don't know if
there are other
other universes out there yeah possibly
it could be so but there is absolutely
not a single data point that indicates
this so therefore we cannot answer these
questions
without indulging in nothing but pure
speculation
so therefore my answer is i don't know
if if there's somebody else who knows it
i would love to hear from them but i
don't know
right let's take some more questions
from the
from the comments so akanksha says i am
a jee aspirant but seeing your videos
make me more interested in history i'm
not able to concentrate on my studies
array
i dream that i should tell people what
they don't know about history by
becoming a historian please help i'm
confused what i should do i am in the
twelfth third akanksha you are very
young
at this age it is very easy to suddenly
get drawn towards this thing and that
thing
at
a very young age like you are it's very
easy
to every week find something new that
you feel passionate about and maybe you
are truly really deeply passionate about
history
and i'm glad it's happened because of
watching my videos but please do not get
confused and please concentrate on your
studies
since you are studying for the jrje it
means you are good in science the thing
is this
you should always have plan a plan b
plan c like i said previously also
i think you should right now focus on
your studies i'm not saying stop
uh
studying history or anything whatever
free time you have study history you're
not going to teach people
history without first imbibing lots of
knowledge which takes years
just getting a history degree is not
going to make you a historian yeah you
will be given the title of historian but
you will not be in a position to teach
anybody anything
a true historian is somebody who has
studied history for like at least 10
years in great detail
just having a degree doesn't make
anybody a historian
right degrees are worthless they're just
scraps of paper especially in the indian
education system so what i would suggest
is this you go ahead with your studies
do you do your 12th do you do the jee
get into an iit
uh become an engineer or whatever it is
that you that you are planning to become
and also in the meanwhile keep studying
history whatever you find interesting
and
maybe 10 years in the future
you can change your career and
profession and say that now i want to
become a historian because now i have a
solid foundation in history
so always take a long term approach and
always have multiple plans
plan a plan b plan c and you can do two
things in parallel why can't you right
so i'm very glad that you are
interested in history that much but
please don't give up your main thing
which is your studies
because it's like this
this country
india
needs
millions of engineers and scientists
tens of millions of engineers and
scientists because this country is a
broken country it needs to be built it
needs to be it needs to be rebuilt
it doesn't mean need millions of
historians maybe a hundred good
historians are enough right now
so i would say that try and figure out
in what way you can serve
your country and your civilization best
i'm sure you can do it through history
as well but that will take time
so give yourself 10 years
in which you do your own study of
history it doesn't have to be a
structured study of history
just read whatever interests you but
also
focus on a primary career which can be
primary for about the next 10 years and
then maybe you can make a change so
that's what i would say
so
don't let your sudden desire to study
history derail
the plan that you already have
that's what i would say
all the best
all right all right what do we have
um
akash rather says why were so many
prehistoric animals so big you know
there were lots of tiny prehistoric
animals lots of them
but we don't find that record in the
fossil
we don't find the remains in the fossil
record why
because tiny fossils don't catch
anyone's eyes
there are many animals that have soft
bodies no no no skeleton for instance
jellyfish
jellyfish don't have skeletons right so
you will never find them in the fossil
record there are so many animals you
will never find in the fossil record you
will only notice the huge ones
so that's why it looks like all the
prehistoric animals were enormous
but that is not the case
you see when you only have a few data
points it looks like everything was like
that
the prehistoric
environment and ecosystem was teeming
with all kinds of life all different
kinds of life many of them are
most of them are permanently lost
so we can't truly recreate
a proper picture of what the world was
like 100 million years before today for
instance
right
and all the fossils that catch your
attention and become famous are the ones
of big animals tyrannosaurus rex rex
apatosaurus brontosaurus triceratops
uh iguanodons
and many other
various animals
but equal source for instance the the
water reptiles and so on so that's what
i can see you know it's not like all
prehistoric animals were very big there
must have been lots and lots of i would
say there must have been many many more
smaller animals that have been lost
in
the passage of history
okay this is a question i have got about
10 000 times until now
karthik has been asking this week after
week
is d evolution or backward evolution
possible during ramayana and mahabharata
people were taller and stronger
intellectuals in us so have we
de-evolved there is no such thing as
forward evolution or backward evolution
there's only evolution time only goes in
one direction as far as as we can see
so evolution only happens
in time there is another thing is what
is the starting point of evolution i
think it's a unicellular organism but
then evolution took place in various
directions
depending on the kind of environment we
had on the planet and the kind of
ecosystem and competition we had among
the different different species so there
is not something is backward devolution
or something right
evolution is just one direction
unidirectional
now during rama and mahabharata people
were taller and stronger what evidence
do we have of that
we did find evidence of somewhere in up
or something of
of more ancient indians about 30 40 000
years before today and the average
height among these people was about six
feet or six feet one one inches
so in the past indians reached their
genetic potential
in recent times what's happened is that
because of the past 1000 years of
disaster in india
the enforced famines artificial famines
hundreds of artificial farming indians
the diet became terrible
indians were just struggling to stay
alive that's why the height decreased oh
average height but today if you look at
the generation z kids they're all much
taller so we are again going back
towards our
genetic potential so indians have always
been a tall and strong people
but we don't know when the ramayana
happened when the maharaja happened many
people have made claims there is no
proof nothing has been corroborated so
please don't tell me that so-and-so is
at this date it is proven it's not
proven
so we don't know for sure when the
ramayana happened when the mahabharata
happened so we don't know at that time
what was the average height of indians
and how do we know that they were more
intellectual than us we have always been
a very intellectual people
even today we have people of the same
intelligence that we had five thousand
or ten thousand years ago
but today the academic system is such a
it destroys people's intelligence and
curiosity and inquisitiveness
it hammers your intelligence out of you
so it's not that people are stupid today
or their or their iq points have
decreased it's just that the system
doesn't allow
talent
to flourish
right so we haven't de-evolved we are
the same people
we need to rediscover our greatness
you are all great people maybe you don't
know it
believe it
and find the greatness within that's
what i would say
okay saurabh and her say about
um what's your view on the cr7 statue
erected erected in goa
your thoughts on ronaldo's statue and
goa both political view and sports
development view you know a statue
doesn't develop sports
and if you want to honor a sports person
i would want you to honor your own
people
is cristiano ronaldo an indian
is he a goan
yeah i have nothing against the guy he's
one of the greatest footballers of all
time clearly one of the top two
footballers
most likely of the 21st century and one
of the greatest footballers that we know
of
in the past hundred years maybe maybe
one of the top ten so yeah he's great
but why do we need to honor him and put
make a statue of him go here
spending our resources
it kind of points to the
slave-mindedness of indians
many people in goa believe that they are
more portuguese than indians for some
reason this is a this is the fact
many people in goa support brazil in the
world cup many indians for some reason
support brazil in the world cup i i
failed to understand what's so great
about brazil
whenever brazil plays argentina i
support argentina whenever brazil plays
france i support france i don't see why
there is so much love for brazil and
portugal also
in india
what is the reason for that
the portuguese colonized india do you
know the atrocities they perpetrated in
india
so why are the victims or the
descendants of the victims of those
horrific atrocities why are they so
enamored with portugal
this is the slave mindset that people
talk about many indians of the slave
mindedness
mental colonization it is it is sad to
say this i have nothing against
cristiano ronaldo but why do we need to
erect a statue of that guy here in india
it just doesn't make any sense
politic maybe there's some political
dimension to that i don't know what it
is in sports development you want to
develop sports
make more stadiums and make them
accessible to the grassroots people
that's how you develop sports give them
facilities to in which to
develop themselves athletically
and play sports that's how you develop
sports
everybody can watch
cristiano ronaldo play on whatever
screen they have everybody has a screen
now so why didn't why do you need a
statue for
for developing sports makes no sense
whatsoever so i am disappointed about
this
all right
um
let us see what else we have
um we indians are idle worshippers
that's why ronaldo and brazil and messi
brazil in portugal all right sir if
that's
your perspective all right
how was the indian government involved
in remo removing the hindu monarchy of
nepal
now this is an interesting question
let me find let me try and find
some sources
me see hang on let me find
okay let me share my screen
shall i do that
let me share my screen and
one second give me a minute i will share
the screen and show you what happened
so this is a this is an article in dna
india
it says
it's it quotes
the ex-special director of the raw
and he has revealed that the r a raw and
aw raw
throughout the monarchy in nepal
so the espionage was not just limited to
ensure unity among various political
parties but also raising assets in nepal
to carry out operations under utmost
secrecy what in 1990 they launched a
spectacular covert operation to bring
down absolute monarchy
in nepal
paving the way for constitutional
democracy
so you can read this article it happened
during the time of mr gandhi mr rajeev
gandhi
and essentially what happened is that
india supported the nepalese maoists
and
engineered the eventual overthrow of the
hindu monarchy of nepal
so read this article it is in dna india
and this is the title you can pause the
screen in the future and check it out
so that's your answer my friends that's
your answer
that's how india overthrew the
hindu monarchy of nepal
okay what else do we have
um
michelangelo michelangelo says could the
james webb telescope help us trace an
alien civilization
it possibly could so the james webb
space telescope is the successor to the
hubble space telescope it's a way more
powerful telescope it's got a much
bigger lens and it's much lighter and
it's going to be placed in the l2
lagrange point
in the earth's shadow about a million
and a half kilometers away from earth
and it's going to see the universe in a
totally different light spectrum the the
infrared and then and the
yeah mainly the infrared spectrum so
it's a time machine essentially it's
going to go back and show us the very
beginning of the first structures in the
universe the first stars the first
galaxies it's also be is going to be
able to look at exoplanets with more
detail it has spectrometers that will
tell us the kind of composition the
atmospheres of these exoplanets have
and we may be able to possibly detect
signs of alien life or alien
civilizations so yes
in short this telescope could actually
give us the first indications
of alien life or alien civilizations
on
planets that are not part of the solar
system exoplanets
this could certainly happen the moment
this telescope goes online after it's
calibrated it's going to start showing
us things we've never seen before but
it's still a
long way away from
from its final destination it has many
more procedures that it needs to do
successfully before it can be actually
deployed and considered to be
operational
so there are many hurdles still left to
overcome but yeah if it succeeds in in
uh
functioning properly is going to
open up entire new vistas of the of the
universe to us
all right some other questions another
science question space is expanding like
an inflating balloon all bodies are
moving away from each other like dots on
the inflating balloon yeah
then how do you explain blue shifts
which means the body is coming towards
us
the universe is expanding on the largest
cosmological scales
of the order of parsecs which is like
you know the thing is that the local
local space
in on in local scales like the local
galactic super cluster gravity overcomes
the expansion of the universe so
in in local distances
in the local supercluster
region
of our galaxy you will find that
gravitational attraction over is able to
overcome the expansion of the universe
and that's why the andromeda galaxy is
moving towards the milky way galaxy you
know in about four to five billion years
from today the two galaxies will merge
so if you look at the andromeda galaxy
you will find that it is blue shifted
it's moving towards us at about 300
kilometers per second or something like
that roughly
so you will find blue shift and see the
entire universe is in motion all the
local galaxies and other components of
the universe local components are in
motion some may be moving away some will
be moving towards you so that's why you
find some objects are blue shifted but
most
objects are redshifted especially the
ones further away from us so that's how
it is so that's why you will find that
some
local objects are indeed blue shifted
like the andromeda galaxy it is indeed
coming towards us yes
hmm okay
was it a good idea to decline the unsc
offer the second time as it would have
deteriorated our relations with soviet
union and china it was the soviet union
that made the offer
so why will it did it deteriorate
india's relations with the so with the
ussr see
the first offer was made in 1950
a permanent seat on the u.n security
council with the veto status the
americans made this
our great
pm sheree neroji said no give it to
china first in 1955 the u.s and the ussr
together made a second offer
again shiri nehru said give it to china
first we don't want it and mr tharur
shashi tharur
he wrote in 2003 that there was an offer
in 1953 as well
so it looks like there were three offers
mr tharu wrote this in his book
so there's no question of so many people
making fake claims even mr thoru who's a
great lover and worshiper of shri nehru
he himself has
said this that the offer was made
an offer was made in 1953 so where is
the question of deteriorating relations
with the ussr the ussr itself was
involved in making the offers and china
was not some huge great power in those
days it was it was a
country that was recovering from a
disastrous civil war india was a more
powerful religion at the time
so who cares if the chinese don't like
it
you have to look out for your your
national interest first lots of people
will not like it when you become
stronger and they are still not strong
enough so who cares what people like
it was not a good idea idea to decline
an offer that would have made india's
position internationally way more
powerful
what stupidity it was
so the indian prime minister
put another country's national interest
ahead of his country's national interest
who is he supposed to serve
is it supposed to serve the people of
india and the country of india or is it
supposed to serve china
what is the
duty of the prime minister of india i
mean am i am i mistaken somewhere
strange really strange
maybe not so strange
maybe not
all right um
let's
let's see this one
okay so i have read on quora
that the gdp of india the gross domestic
product of india was highest during the
mughal empire
but indians were living in poverty is it
true
okay let's take a look let me share my
screen again and show you uh
okay let's take a look at india's share
of the world's gdp
so this is
uh the research of the
of the economist angus medicine you can
see the share of the world gdp of india
china the middle east western europe and
the us
over the past 2000 years it's a rough
approximation i don't entirely agree
with this i think india's share was much
higher actually but even if we take this
because this is the gold standard
nowadays
so the first 1000 years are represented
very briefly and you can see india was
the highest now the so-called mughals
they came into power in india in the
15th in in the 16th century middle of
the 16th century
uh with barber
so that's somewhere around here
there is somewhere around here if you
can see my mouse pointer it's when india
and china's gdp was more or less the
same india's gdp was declining because
india was under turkic occupation for
half a century for half a million by
this time
so after 1000 india's gdp comes down
so during the mughal empire which is
between 15
1500 so or so until 1857
india's gdp was down in the 1700s it
went ahead of china again and then it
crashed completely because that's when
the east india company rule starts
and you can see that as india's gdp is
declining western europe udp is
increasing
at the same time it is essentially the
loot of india's treasures and wealth and
everything the plunder and and europe is
being enriched mostly britain
at the expense of india
right
so what the mughals did was
they um the turks not just the mughals
the overall all the turks they occupied
india and they destroyed india's culture
they destroyed all the temples all the
universes everything and they reduced
indians to to poverty indians were
living in subjugation but the money of
india more or less to some extent stayed
in india you can see the decline is
already happening because much of that
money
significant portions were being sent to
to central asia
to arabia et cetera but still you cannot
you don't see a tremendous decline you
do see a decline so clearly a
significant amount of money was going
out of india
but it is not as bad as what the british
did so the mughals the turks
they did plunder india they did send
much of india's money outside
to various other places the islamic
world essentially
and they destroyed india's culture they
tried to stamp out india's culture what
the british did was they completely
drained india of all its wealth as you
can see
completely destroyed india's economy
totally the turks destroyed india's
culture and the british destroyed
india's economy completely
so that is what i can say about this i
hope it gives you a reasonably good idea
of what really
happened in the past 1000 years of
india's humiliation
the millennium
of humiliation
okay
what books were burned were there in
nalanda university that was burned
you know we don't have the record so how
can i tell you what books with this are
we don't have the records the records of
india's history of india's science of
everything
it is not just one university nalanda
vikram shilla taksha sheila sharda pitt
udantapuri
there are so many universities that we
don't even know of anymore because they
have been flattened
all of these universities they had
immense libraries
every single topic under the universe
that you can think of was there
the records of 10 000 years of india's
history
all were burned
all the ancient indian treaties is on
science mathematics astronomy philosophy
religion vedic texts buddhist texts
jaina texts other texts everything you
can imagine everything was there
just just one library the naland library
it burned for several months can you
imagine how many millions of books were
there
so
do you want me to list them do you think
i'll be able to list them
i can tell you what
overall topics must have been there
but even that is speculation there must
be some so much more that we don't know
of
so that's what i can say sir i hope it
kind of answers your question
let's take some other more questions
haha
so ahmanja says
finally the home ministry has refused
fcra renewal
for the missionaries of charity what are
your thoughts on this decision
personally i think that this is a great
decision because several foreign funded
ngos used to stop the development of the
country
yes i agree with your assessment i think
it's a very good move
better late than never see when you have
an ngo that gets money from abroad
it's usually being used to
exert some sort of foreign interference
in india other countries they will look
out for their national interest their
personal interest why will they care
about india's interests
we have had engine ngos and missionaries
in india for
since since 1947
what have they done for india
in what way have they uplifted india
this woman teresa
mother teresa the caller she was in
kolkata for many decades what did she do
for the people of kolkata
all she did was convert tens of
thousands of people to christianity but
did she uplift anybody from poverty she
had access to millions of dollars of
funding millions a million dollars was a
big deal
20 30 40 years ago
what did she do
so the entire purpose of these
missionaries and all that is
they they don't care about india's
interests
they don't want to uplift anybody from
poverty they don't want to alleviate
anyone's suffering
it's all about
foreign
interference in india's internal
matters
you know in the ngo industry is the
biggest scam in india
there are more ngos in india than there
are schools
you know that
there are more ngos in india than there
are schools plus hospitals to put
together
if there are so many ngos why isn't
india now all developed and why why
aren't all the problems already resolved
because the entire purpose of every ngo
is to solve problems right
so so why
are there still so many problems in
india because the ngos are creating more
problems they are nothing but tools of
foreign interference in india
and when foreign money is pouring in
it's always for certain foreign purposes
not indian purposes
it's not to
make india stronger or better it's too
it's to serve a purpose
that the funding
entity
wants to achieve
so i am really glad that this missionary
nonsense has been
the fcra approval has been
has been
not renewed it's a very welcome step i'm
glad it has been done finally
so i would say it's a very welcome step
good job sirs
okay
please give me a brief on at the feet of
the master by judo krishnamurti i
haven't read it sorry very sorry
i haven't read every book in the world
uh so yeah sorry can't i can't answer
this question
um
the supreme court is taking leave for
more than 100 days
keeping 40 million cases open
yes sir your your your
observation
is reasonably accurate
um
what else do we have
can puranas and upanishads be written
even today i don't think so
i don't think so
upanishads are what are open puranas are
essentially
uh
records of ancient history
upanishads i believe are commentaries on
the vedic texts so i suppose somebody
with enough irradiation
and
knowledge could possibly write a new
openness upon issue today it could
possibly happen
do we have anybody alive today who has
that much knowledge that much
understanding the depth of understanding
required the intellectual
caliber required
to do that because you need two things
first of all you need a very high level
of intelligence
secondly you need an encyclopedic
understanding
of the vedas and other upanishads so if
somebody
does have these two
very difficult qualities in in the same
person then certainly it's possible to
write new person certainly it may be
possible
puranas i'm not quite sure i would say
most likely not
right let us see some more questions
uh
many questions i've
i've answered before
see for instance this question is
sanskrit the mother of all
languages and influence many other
languages across asia and europe i have
so many videos about sanskrit about the
the entire rn invasion controversy the
rn invasion myth please please look at
those videos there is so much
content about these matters on this
channel
please look into it
so i have essentially already answered
these questions you know so that's why
i'm saying please look into it
um
once again
i have expressed this very
very
clearly
and i've gone into significant detail
about this
about mr gandhi's role in india's
partition
i have several videos about this not
just from this channel other channels as
well
so please look at that
okay prasha prasad says india has plans
of inviting the central asian countries
on republic day and obviously there will
be talks on defense and trade and
strategic relations
and many other things the do you think
that russia will allow this oh i mean
who are they to not allow this
do you think that russia will allow this
or have a close watch at this as central
asia is russia's
natural sphere of influence and
ex-soviet members and what will china's
reaction if this happens as the bri
project can be endangered
um first of all who is russia would not
allow this
secondly
are we interfering in russia's natural
sphere of influence are we sending
troops there are we sending engineers
there are we constructing infrastructure
no
we are inviting
the
presidents of five central asian
republics
as chief guests
what is wrong with that so what is
central asia let's
in case you guys are not aware let me
show you what central asia is
um
one second
let me share my
screen so this is what central asia
looks like
this
region
uh north of india northwest of india
historically this was uttara madra
the uttara madra
region
and that is now central asia so there
are five
republics in central asia
right
so there is kazakhstan tajikistan
uzbekistan kyrgyzstan and turkmenistan
kazakhstan the capital
and their presidents are being invited
kasim tokayev of kazakhstan
uh imam ali rahman of tajikistan
of uzbekistan
i don't remember the president of
kazakhstan and the great the great
president of turkmenistan guru bangla
birdie mahal madoff
so these are the gentlemen we are
inviting for talks and for
for building better relations i see
absolutely no reason for the russians to
get alarmed about that
this is a standard thing that people do
and it's it's it's nice to do that
so uh what was the question again
this was the question
so russia they may keep a close watch on
this
they are welcome to we have nothing to
hide
uh what will be china's reaction if this
happens
well china will also keep an eye on this
can their bri project be in danger i
don't see any reason for the project to
be in danger india is not creating any
infrastructure beyond india right now
and even if india has plans to do that
it will take a lot of money to do that
billions of dollars and there's no plan
to do that so i don't see any reason for
anybody to be alarmed if the chinese
want to keep an eye on it they are
welcome to if the russians want to keep
an eye on it on it they are welcome to
india and russia have good relations and
good cooperation so
it's just a way of
strengthening india's relationships with
various countries
historically central asia has been
uttarakh
essentially uttara madra it's it's been
part of india's fear of influence and
there is no harm in maintaining good
friendly and constructive relations with
these countries
and i think it's a very good move from
the geopolitical perspective as well so
i'm really glad that the prime minister
has decided upon this course of action
for
the upcoming
republic day great job
okay let's take
puranas are not history
ramayana and
are but puranas are only meant to
explain knowledge of vedas through
stories
thank you for the gyan thank you very
much thank you for your perspective
um what else do we have
can you please put some light on the
death of sri lanka
i am not an expert in this matter i have
not read
enough about this to give you a
definitive or even a quasi-definitive
answer
as to what really happened
but maybe somebody is an expert on this
and maybe i will
invite that person for a discussion on
this channel maybe soon so watch out for
that and then your question will be
answered
oh
what else do we have
um
some interesting questions who is
yamnaya
who is yamnya well nobody is yamnia
today
the yamnya people were the uh
where a group of horse riding men
horse riders
who invaded europe about four and a half
or five thousand years before today
when the saraswati hindus phase of
india's civilization was in progress
so these men
horse riders warriors brutally violent
people
these guys they invaded europe from
somewhere in the east
and they rampaged across europe
killed most of the men
and then they had children with the
european women
and their descendants are the people of
europe modern-day europe
and their
lineage was mostly r1b
their patrilineal paternal lineage was
mostly r1b which is a descendant of the
r1
indian lineage
so these guys who are called yamnaya
today
were descendants of indians
their origin at some point in time was
india their ancestors had come from
india
and then these guys they rampaged across
europe in a very short time
and
western publications say that they
conducted the greatest genocide the
worst genocide the world has ever seen
and they're talking about their own
ancestors
so that's who the yamnaya are i have
videos about that detailed videos in
which i have spoken about this in more
detail
please look into it
huh what led humans to practice
cannibalism i can't imagine why human
humans would want to do that i think
during times of starvation like like the
like in the 1920s 1930s in ukraine for
instance the holodomor famine which was
engineered by joseph stalin at that time
there was widespread cannibalism i also
have heard read about this that
during the artificial famines that mao
setong
engineered in china at that time also
there was widespread carnivalism so
typically
just to stay alive people will consume
human flesh of those who have already
died that sort of terrible terrible
situations were there in the 20th
century
i we also know about this plane crash in
the indian mountains there was this
football team
there was on a plane that crashed in
south america in the andes mountains
high up
high altitude and they were trapped
there for i think months
many of them died so just to stay alive
they consumed the flesh
of those who had died just out of
desperation
so it these some such instances we know
of
but there have also been certain
cultures that practiced cannibalism so
what leads them to do that i'm not quite
sure
i'm sure some anthropologists would be
able to answer that so maybe
maybe so we can look into that but i
don't have a definitive answer as to why
such practices would evolve it's
typically done among small tribal
communities a tribe is not a
civilization or a culture it's just an
isolated band of individuals who lives
together typically deep inside some
jungle and they're isolated for
centuries or so
so they develop such practices sometimes
you hear about such practices being
practiced in the past among the
tribal naga people in northeastern india
so they had this practice
and if you look at the jungles of borneo
i think cannibalism was practiced there
it's there too these are again tribal
communities and
i think even in the south pacific
islands the polynesian islands you had
cannibalism being practiced there as
well
uh
so yes there are certain tribal
communities that you that had this
practice why they did why they had it
what was the origin of this i am not
quite sure but it's an interesting topic
maybe we can
maybe i can find somebody to discuss
this with interesting
right let's find some other
questions
um
if scientists don't know anything about
dark matter and dark energy
then how do they predict that the
universe will end in this way
we have no predictions
about
the end of the universe we don't know
which way the universe is going to end
we have certain speculations
maybe there'll be a big rip maybe
there'll be a big crunch maybe we're in
a cyclic oscillating universe we don't
know we don't have sufficient data to
give any
uh
clear-cut answers as as to what's going
to be the eventual fate of the universe
as you say we don't know anything about
dark matter and dark energy which
together comprises 95 percent of the
matter energy composition of the
universe
and even
of the when we look at the five percent
universe that we can actually possibly
see we understand it only very very in a
very rudimentary fashion we don't even
understand that properly so we have
essentially no clue as to what the
universe is
we do have working technology and all
that because of which we are able to do
these things that gives us the
impression that we are really in control
of everything and we know everything but
we don't so we don't know in what way
the universe is going to end whether
it's going to be a big rip or a big
crunch or whether we have a cyclic
universe or anything of anything at all
so
we don't have predictions as to how the
universe is going to end or what
eventual fate it's going to meet
okay um
what else do we have
um
can sentinels be cannibals
that's what ashutosh is asking so what
he means is the people of the so-called
sentinel island it's an island that is
the name has been given given by the
british so it's part of the uh andaman
nicobar archipelago let me show you
where it is why not let's do that give
me a minute
let me pull up
a map
and share that with you
so
and once again
one second let me put it up
okay this is the map
so
let's dive into the bay of bengal
where is sentinel island
that's the question
i think it is this one here
this is called the north sentinel island
it is
in the andaman archipelago let's take a
look at how it is
as you can see it's just
forest
and you will find a shipwrecked ship
somewhere here
if we can still see it
it was somewhere here
yeah there it is so this is a shipwreck
which happened a couple of decades about
three decades ago maybe in the 1980s or
so so this is the uh one of the last
this island is the home of one of the
last uncontacted peoples
in the world they are mostly uncontacted
so there is a group of people living on
this island
they have been stuck here for about 30
or 40 000 years
so
they probably were migrating from africa
to some place via the sea route
and they got shipwrecked here possibly
and they got stranded on this island and
they have been stranded here for
30 or 40 000 years
and
we don't know what their practices are
they are very hostile to any
outsider
uh there are reports of people having
been killed when they ventured onto this
island
the last such
incident was about about a year or two
ago when some american idiot went there
with the bible he wanted to convert them
to christianity and they greeted him
with
arrows and they killed him
so this guy went there illegally because
the indian government has decreed that
nobody is allowed on this island these
people will be left alone and they will
not be interfered with
so essentially this is an autonomous
island which is under india's protection
it is obviously part of india but indian
law doesn't run over on this island we
have decided that we will not interfere
with anything they do
so could they be cannibals i mean we
have no evidence of them
practicing cannibalism but it's clearly
a very interesting set of people we
don't know what is the population
today maybe it's a few hundred maybe
it's a few dozens we don't quite know
uh
they were affected by the uh 2004
andaman
mega earthquake
but they survived it i think the indian
air force sent helicopters to see if
they are okay and i think they were okay
so that's what i can say about these
peoples these people they're a very
interesting group of people
uh
the last one of the last stone age
people still remaining on the planet one
of the last uncontacted people
there was some contact uh in the 19th
century i think
the british went there and they kind of
messed things up
treated them very badly in a variety of
ways and that's why they are so hostile
to outsiders
so that's what we can say about them
are they are they cannibals we have no
evidence that they are cannibals most
likely i think they may not be cannibals
all right let's see some other questions
what are your views on bollywood and its
impact on the common people in india
do you think they propagate
certain narratives like the movies jb
bollywood has a very negative influence
on india i am sure there are certain
good people in bollywood certain good
filmmakers but overall
it has a very negative influence
on the people of india the kind of music
for instance
it doesn't the music the dance and
whatever they represent it doesn't it
does not represent indian culture at all
they are trying to pass off elements of
foreign cultures as indian culture
and
they are very
there is clearly a demonstrable
proven element of hindu phobia that has
been
present in bollywood since the 1970s
1980s onwards today bollywood is
overwhelmingly hindu phobic
and this jbm i haven't seen it i don't
know what it's about but i i'm
i have heard reports of the kind of
uh
ideological slant this move this movie
has
so there is a great deal of hindu phobia
in bollywood and the kind of music they
are
throwing out it's terrible
and that's what's influencing the minds
of the youngsters today
they think all this is cool you know
to dress like a bollywood person to to
behave like a bollywood person to play
those songs good god
so yeah my overall view of bollywood is
very negative unfortunately nothing
nothing against anybody but it's just
what you observe and what's proven right
so
so that's what bollywood is see
typically a film industry represents the
culture of a country if you look at the
french film industry
it is one of france's greatest exports
if you look at japanese films
the japanese enemies
you know animation animated series and
all that they have done so much to
promote japan's culture
and to enhance japan's image worldwide
but if you see bollywood movies they
actually denigrate indian culture
and make india look like a garbage
dump
right so it it actually hurts
india's image and harms india's
reputation globally so that is the kind
of
extremely negative effect bollywood has
so that's that's what it is
okay what else do we have let me take
one more comment
um
okay this is interesting atmeka says
in the battle of the mahabharata there's
a portion in which abhimanyu
arjuna's son
is caught in the chakra view and
brutally murdered by multiple people
for once i can digest that the likes of
duryodhana and dushasan were part of the
group but why were dhrunachari and
kripacharya involved in this heinous
crime
were they really a part of this or has
this been distorted with time
okay
so what is the what was the mahabharata
this this
event that you're referring to it was
part of the great war
called the mahabharata
it was a war right
when you kill somebody
when a soldier
dies
during battle
in a war
can that be considered to be a murder or
a crime
what is the purpose of war when does a
war happen war happens when you're
unable to resolve whatever issues you
have
through diplomacy through negotiations
through talk
so we don't have lord krishna tried
diplomacy
he tried his best to avert bloodshed he
tried his best to avert
war
at the end he realized that it's not
working he has failed and that's why he
said we need to have a war we need to go
into the war so that's why the war
happened
now in war
you're going to resolve your issues
through brutality through violence that
is the nature of war if somebody
dies in war while engaging in battle
that is not a crime
that is not a murder
abhimanyu
was a warrior he was an exceptionally
gifted warrior he was better than most
warriors i know he was 16 years old
he was 16
but he went and participated in the war
he must have killed several enemy
soldiers at least because it was a great
soldier great warrior
one person was not enough to defeat him
and he willingly went into this
formation called the chakra view
and he went inside the chakra with the
objective of killing everyone who was
there
and when somebody comes to kill you it
is your duty to kill them back to try to
kill them
and maybe he was so good that multiple
people had to fight him and kill him
that is the nature of war
there is no right or wrong once a war
starts theory
there is only one objective of war
the only objective in warfare is to
win there is no consolation prize or
second prize you don't get a prize for
participating oh you participated no
there is only one prize which is victory
and typically
the losers they often die
that's just how it is that is the brutal
nature of warfare there is no right or
wrong once you engage in warfare yes in
the past
indian soldiers indian warriors they
engaged they
they observed certain rules and all that
but many of those rules were broken
during the mahabharata war we know that
the pandavas broke some rules because
the core of also broke some rules
that all shows what human nature is
about
but at the end of the day the only
objective is to win and the only
objective is to kill those who want to
kill you
whether it is one person whether it is
500 people doesn't matter
every battle every combat cannot be
one-on-one sometimes you will blunder
into enemy territory and multiple
soldiers will be away available to fight
you in that case 10 people may kill
someone that's just the way it is
there's no right or wrong
so i do not see this
i it doesn't matter whether duryodhan
dushasan or anybody else was part of the
group yes it was a group of people who
killed abhimanyu
and that's just the way it is it's not a
crime
and maybe he was young but then if he
was that young why did he why did he go
into battle he was a trained warrior he
was an exceptional warrior even at the
age of 16 he was a trained killer
so you know what this is just how it
goes
that's just how it is
okay kalyan karthik says nuclear powered
rockets for the future of space travel i
certainly think present-day ones are
rudimentary machines for the obstacles
we may face in the future in future
space observation
so people have tried all kinds of fuels
for rockets
they have tried hydrogen peroxide
essentially steam rockets
they have tried uh it's all about the
specific impulse of the fuel fuel that
you're using so if you trade take
aviation fuel which is kerosene if you
take petrol the specific impulse is not
quite great uh when you use
other fuels like hydrogen and oxygen
that reaction
this specific impulse is much higher so
you need something with a very high
specific impulse
for rocket propulsion for in order to
break free of the earth's gravity by uh
by going past escape velocity
so pres in the present day we have a
number of fuels
hypergolic fuels etc
which are used for rocket propulsion
now nuclear power is certainly something
that would be even more powerful but uh
there is no
we don't have a way of controlling a
nuclear explosion right so i think in
the 1970s 60s perhaps
there was
um
a project in america
maybe it was a nasa project i think
in which they were trying to develop or
they were they were looking at the
possibility of developing rockets
powered by nuclear explosions
and the the concept was shown to be
viable
so it's certainly possible
to send a rocket to mars by atomic bomb
it's certainly possible and such rockets
will by necessity have to be huge
mega monster rockets not these thin
little things which go up today
and you can send hundreds of people on
that if you can make it safe enough
so it is certainly
possible but of course nuclear fallout
is not good for the atmosphere for the
environment
it's going to release radiation
which is going to be harmful to life so
there will
first be the need to find a way to
ensure somehow if it is even possible
to ensure that this nuclear fallout
isn't a problem it doesn't contaminate
the environment the atmosphere
so technically it is certainly possible
it may even be a superior form of travel
it may allow you to send hundreds of
tons of payload into into orbit and
beyond
but there's always a problem of the
nuclear fall out that will contaminate
the atmosphere so if that can somehow be
resolved it's a cert it's certainly a
viable way
and it is and possibly a superior way of
engaging in space travel so very
interesting question
right
right let's see what else we have
um
many questions are being repeated
okay
[Laughter]
is it true that the cholas
swam across the indian ocean since they
were rudimentary at technology
okay
let me take this seriously and let's
take a look at the indian ocean
let's take a look at the indian ocean
the cholas were essentially
in present-day tamil nadu madurai was it
let's say they were from here and they
had to call they wanted to conquer
southeast asia
starting from java sumatra etc this
region here if you can see my mouse
pointer so let's calculate the distance
from here
roughly from here to here let's say
that's 2000 kilometers
now
is it
possible for a human being
to swim 2 000 kilometers
is it possible for a human being
to swim a hundred kilometers
is it possible to swim two thousand
kilometers and then have the strength to
conquer an entire
empire
does it make any sense
and who says that they were very
rudimentary technology
you are making this
presupposition my dear friend
that the cholas were rudimentary
technology
what what
what makes you think this
the cholas were a very sophisticated
empire
they had a very they had the most
powerful navy of that time on the planet
they were a maritime empire
they had marines you know marines marine
soldiers
they put those marines on their ships
they sailed across the entire indian
ocean the bay of bengal
and then they reached
java sumatra
and after that long journey
they conquered that entire empire and
they not only conquered that they
conquered the entirety of southeast asia
vietnam thailand cambodia laos
philippines as well can you do that by
swimming
want you need to carry weaponry
equipment
and much more
okay so i hope i have answered this
question
you would need to be
super olympic questions i mean uh a
thousand times superior maybe a million
times superior to the best olympic
swimmer
in order to achieve that that
that feat
all right what else do we have
what else do we have
any interesting questions
okay let me take a question from
a previous comment
okay sagar says please speak about
indian math books
etc
are these books better than our
modern school texts do they have any
relevance in today's
modern world
so let me speak about the lilavati
so the lilavati
was written by one of our greatest
scientists mathematician as well as
astronomers whose name was bhaskara
bhaskar acharya he is known as bhaskar
ii
he is supposed to have lived in the 12th
century
a.d
that's what is believed
so he wrote his greatest work was called
the siddhanta shiromani
which is believed to have been written
in that time 12th century so this was a
book
this work comprised essentially three
sections the first was called the
lilavathi which was about 13 chapters
it was a book of arithmetic and
measurement the second section was
called the bija ganet
which was a book which was a treatise on
algebra
and the third was called ganet adi
which essentially covered astronomy
so the leelawater which you speak about
is a book of arithmetic and measurement
mostly
so bhaskara had a kid
a child it was a girl child her name was
lilavathi he wrote this book
to get her interested in mathematics and
to teach her the fundamentals of
arithmetic
and measurement
this book is available today i have it
somewhere
in english translation it's an excellent
book for kids to learn math from it's
very relevant even today it's an
excellent book to learn math from
arithmetic from
and
the existence of this book also debunks
this great claim that is made that oh my
god indians
they were patriarchal misogynistic
girls did not have access to education
and all that
come on he wrote this book for his
daughter to teach her math
so you know so that's what it is about
there are so many such texts
from other great mathematicians and
scientists as well but if you ask me
about the lead this is what i can say
about that
you can buy it online i'm sure this book
very good book
okay do we have any other interesting
questions
um
i am not
an expert in this dynasty i'm very sorry
maybe i will study it
sometime in the future and if i do i may
get back to you about this but
i am not the right person to
give you any details about this dynasty
okay anything else any other good
questions i'm sure there are thousands
but i need to find them
what else do we have
okay let's see this
uh what's your opinion about the 1964
blue book alien interview
so i am not aware of this interview but
i am aware of something called the
project blue book which is supposedly a
top secret thing or something
in which the americans took alien took
reports of alien contact very seriously
they took reports of ufos very seriously
and they actually had a team
investigating all of this
and i'm not sure if it has been
declassified or not but apparently they
found evidence apparently
but some of these
reports may have been genuine and there
may actually have been
unexplained and unexplainable
flying
object phenomena that may possibly have
some alien origin
so there was this project called
project blue book
i think it has been covered in
in movies or or serials as well perhaps
i'm not quite sure but that's what i can
say about this so it's certainly
something very that's very interesting
but personally i have never found any
unequivocal
incontrovertible proof of alien
visitation on earth so
it's certainly something that's very
interesting but we still don't have
proof from from what i know
okay where are we verticals do we have
please tell us about yuri benjamin of
about a subversion theory so this is
something that's
big
i can tell you in short who he was he
was a soviet defector
to the united states
uh
he defected from india
so he was a very big fan of india
apparently he was very interested in
indian culture
and he eventually became disillusioned
with the soviet union with the ussr he
was apparently
a member of the kgb which is the you
know what it is
their secret service it used to be
and he became disillusioned with the
methods and everything of the ussr he
decided to defect to the west
so he did this defection from india
from new delhi most likely
he disguised himself as a tourist and
escaped to greece and from greece he
went
he eventually ended up in the united
states
and i think a couple of his lectures are
quite famous they may be available on
youtube
in which he speaks about the subversion
theory
which essentially says that the ussr
its objective was to subvert
american society
ideologically
and hollow out the u.s from within
so
what he claimed is that
the primary objective of the kgb was not
to indulge in engage in espionage
on american soil it was to use american
institutions
american culture
and american systems
to subvert the minds of americans
make them pro-left
pro-marxism pro-socialism
pro-all that
and make them move away from what is
known as american values capitalism all
that
so that's the claims he made in the
1990s
it's on it's on video record
now i will leave it to you to judge
whether such a shift has happened or not
in american society that's the
interesting part so what i would
recommend is instead of asking me what
should we watch the video i think it's
available online he has
explained this in great detail in one of
these video lectures
so check it out it's very interesting
okay
any other questions
what do you think of bob lazar's story
if you don't know please research a bit
yes sir your wish is my command i will
do more i will do more research
what else do we have
okay
bye-bye
if you're leaving
uh
okay rishabh says there are similarities
between our mythology and foreign
mythologies like greek rome etc
so when and how do you think these
stories travel outside i have spoken
about this in great detail in my
previous videos i have short clips about
this as well you will see clear clear
similarities between the indian vedic
pantheon of gods
the greek pantheon the roman pantheon
the
nordic teutonic viking pantheon the
slavic gods it's all the same
it's all the same i have explained in
detail how this would have happened
it's because of out of five out of india
migrations
thousands of years before today which
are recorded in indian literature
multiple waves of migrations out of
india
right so i have spoken about this in
great deal not in great detail but in
significant detail
please check out my older videos i have
hundreds of videos on the channel do a
simple search
you'll find it
okay
what's my opinion about shivaji's death
the great chatrapati shivaji maharaj
he died very young didn't he he died at
the age of 50 i think around 50
most likely 55-0 itself
and
clearly he died very young 50 is too
early for somebody to die
so so the
question has always remained
was his death natural death was he
poisoned
i think
i will have to
bring in an expert to discuss this
it's a very good question
i personally don't have answers to this
it's clearly
a very early death
and he was a vigorous man
he was mostly a healthy man we don't
know of any health issues that he may
have had
so it's quite strange he died so early
so yeah may it was there some some foul
play
uh done we i i personally don't know but
maybe i will i will call someone to
answer this question in the future
somebody who is an expert in this matter
in the in the history of the maratha
empire
but it's clearly something that sounds a
little fishy to me he lied to young
okay
do they have any other interesting
questions
is socialism feasible and will it slow
down or f
or hasten
technological growth haven't you seen
the history of socialism in india
from 1947 onwards india
followed
socialism
right
the word socialist was even inserted
inserted into india's constitution
have you not seen what happened in india
in that time
did india do well
as a socialist
nation
did you see an exponential increase or
even a slow increase in technological
growth
that is your answer my friends
okay
what else do we have
um
this question again
it's indian civilization
is there a possibility that the universe
will live in is created as the
simulation by some intelligent life
there is a possibility yes it's not
it is certainly
a plausible hypothesis do we have
evidence no
but it's certainly plausible
so yes there is a possibility
there is a possibility some people say
that this is nonsense you cannot think
of this but you know what
you have to keep your an open mind don't
become narrow-minded and dogmatic
there is certainly a possibility that we
are living inside a simulation
and i have spoken about this also many
times in the past so yes
it is
possible
happened after lord krishna's death well
the rest of indian history happened
after his death
so essentially he installed pariksit as
the emperor
was the son of abhimanyu
so the pandava lineage continued and
then there were southern certain other
descendants of this lineage and then the
rest of indian history happened so
that's what i can say
in brief
okay
is it true that hitler invited a
sanskrit scholar to germany
to develop nukes so is there something
in the sanskrit language that allows you
that gives you knowledge of nuclear
physics
why do you do you need a knowledge of
sanskrit to develop nuclear weapons
so as far as i know this is not the case
is jainism older than hinduism
[Laughter]
uh there is no evidence
that either or is more see
jainism
hinduism
buddhism everything else islam which
came out of india is the same culture
it's thousands of years old
these are not separate religions
please drill this into your heads
jainism is not a separate religion from
hinduism buddhism is not a separate
religion this is all part of the dharmic
tradition it is all part of what we call
saranthan dharma
therefore this question doesn't make any
sense at all
okay
all right
what are your views on the new education
policy nep the new education system
uh i think it's like
placing a band-aid on a gunshot wound
it does nothing
it's completely pointless maybe there
are some small tiny cosmetic
improvements here or there
but overall it's the same
colonial system that is being continued
i have several episodes purely dedicated
to education
please take a look
in which i have spoken about this these
things in great detail in great detail
all right
uh did the people from the mahabharat
and ramayana era live longer than people
who live today than us
we don't know
how do we know
we don't have records
we don't have data
we don't have hard data
right
so how do we
how do i answer the question
there are claims there are many people
who claim that humans lived for hundreds
of years
but by where is the evidence
where is the evidence for that and we
know today that human life that human
life typically doesn't extend much
beyond 100 years some people are known
to have lived into their 130s maybe 140
at most
so biologically we know
that the human lifespan has a certain
limit
we have evidence for
centuries essentially for thousands of
years maybe beyond
two three
hundred thousand years of homo sapiens
and we have never found found a skeleton
of homo sapiens
that has lived beyond a hundred or 121
30 years
because you can date the age
with scientific tools
so there is no evidence that humans
lived for centuries or any such thing so
the answer i can give you is
there is no evidence that we have of
longer lifespans
during the ramayana or mahabharata eras
we don't even know exactly when these
eras
happened
because we have lost the evidence
so
that's what i can say
all right what else do we have
do we have evidential history of jainism
before mahavira
it can debunk ait as i think jainism
originated after harper and vedic age
people are the lineage of harappans we
have no evidence for any of these things
we have no evidence that the vedic age
people
are the lineage of harappans they came
after harappa we have no evidence of
that i think the vedic the vedic age
happened before
these great urban cities
so what we call the harappan age is this
great urbanization of ancient india
which happened about 5000 years before
today
the vedic age if you if you read the
vedic texts the rig veda etc they depict
a rural
india
they depict a pastoral lifestyle
they do not depict an urban civilization
so clearly the vedic age
was way before
the so-called harappan age of india
right
so that's the first point now
do we have evidential history of jainism
before mahabhira
well according to jaina records
according to jain
tradition
um
vardaman mahavira was the 24th
tirthankar of jainism there were 23
great tirthankars before him
now do we have actual evidence of this
we don't we lost all our ancient records
a thousand years before today
so we have no actual evidence of this
but i see no reason
to not believe the jain tradition so yes
there most likely were 23 great in
tirthankaras before were the one mahavir
and that see that clearly is something
that goes back
centuries if not millennia
but we don't have any actual hard
evidence of the dates or any of any of
that
so today this is where we are we have
lost all the real records of our history
so we only have to
make educated guesses as of today and
indulge in some speculation but i
refuse to say that this is all myths
this is not myths
these are all our ancient traditions
which are all based in reality these
things actually happened
so that's what i can say about it
all right what else do we have
i think uh
yeah it's already nearly two hours so
let's let us wrap it up over over here
right now
so
thank you for the questions it was
wonderful very interesting questions i
took today
and let's keep doing this
let us keep doing this and very soon you
will see
different things on this channel
conversations and other things as well
so
stay tuned for that coming very soon
all right i will see you in next week's
live streams until then take care thank
you very much for your viewership thank
you for everything
and
see you very soon in the next episode